<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>More excellent obseruations of the estate and affaires of Holland In a discourse, shewing how necessarie and conuenient it is for their neighbouring countries, as well as the Netherland prouinces, to trade into the West Indies. ... Faithfully translated out of the Dutch copie.</title>
            <title>Missive daer in kortelijck ende grondigh werdt vertoont, hoe veel de Vereenighde Nederlanden gheleghen is aen de Oost ende West Indische navigatie. English.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 78 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03450</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13573</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104122</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839861</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839861</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4320</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03450)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4320)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1144:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>More excellent obseruations of the estate and affaires of Holland In a discourse, shewing how necessarie and conuenient it is for their neighbouring countries, as well as the Netherland prouinces, to trade into the West Indies. ... Faithfully translated out of the Dutch copie.</title>
                  <title>Missive daer in kortelijck ende grondigh werdt vertoont, hoe veel de Vereenighde Nederlanden gheleghen is aen de Oost ende West Indische navigatie. English.</title>
                  <author>Usselincx, Willem, 1567-ca. 1647.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 37, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By E. A[llde] for Nicholas Bourne and Thomas Archer, and are to be sold at their shops at the Exchange, and the Popes-head-Pallace,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of "Missive daer in kortelijck ende grondigh werdt vertoont, hoe veel de Vereenighde Nederlanden gheleghen is aen de Oost ende West Indische navigatie", sometimes doubtfully attributed to Willem Usselincx.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Netherlands --  Commerce --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  Commerce --  Netherlands Antilles --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Netherlands Antilles --  Commerce --  Netherlands --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4320:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4320:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>MORE EX<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CELLENT OBSER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VATIONS OF THE ESTATE AND AFFAIRES OF HOLLAND. In a diſcourſe, ſhewing how neceſſarie <hi>and conuenient it is for their neighbouring Countries,</hi> as well as the Netherland Prouinces, to Trade into the Weſt Indies. <hi>And by moſt vrgent and good reaſons, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing that by the Weſt Indian Trade now erected in</hi> HOLLAND, <hi>the ſaid Company ſhall receiue great benefit, the Hollanders greater ſeruice, and the Spaniard more hurt, and greater diſaduantage then euer he receiued before.</hi> As alſo the great profit and commodity the ſaid Netherlands haue reaped and receiued, during the time of 24. yeares that the ſaid Company hath Traded into the Eaſt Indies. <hi>Faithfully Tranſlated out of the Dutch Copie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed at London by <hi>E.A.</hi> for <hi>Nicholas Bourne</hi> and <hi>Thomas Archer,</hi> and are to be ſold at their Shops at the <hi>Exchange,</hi> and the <hi>Popes-head-Pallace.</hi> 1622.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:4320:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:4320:2"/>
            <head>MORE EXCELLENT OBSERVATIONS OF the eſtate and affaires <hi>of Holland.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, in conformity of my promiſe to reſolue you of certaine queſtions, in your Letter lately ſent vnto mee, ſet downe; I thought good at this preſent, orderly to make anſwer thereunto, nothing doubting, but that you ſhall thereby receiue good contentment and ſatisfaction.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>The firſt queſtion.</head>
                  <p>Whether it had not beene better and more commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous for the vnited Netherland Prouinces, to haue made a new truce with the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> for twelue yeares more, with leauing of the Eaſt Indian Trade, then by continuing the ſame, to begin warre againe, and to be debarred of the Spaniſh Trade?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>Anſwere.</head>
                  <p>It is true, that friendſhip, commerſe, and conuerſation, are the neceſſary conſequences of peace, according to the generall lawes of nature, of all people, and of all times, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation and commerſe, being ſignes of friendſhip, and of peace, which is denied to no man, but to an enemie.</p>
                  <p>In ſuch manner that there is no example extant, or to be found, that there was euer any treaty of peace made or concluded, with the vnited Netherland Prouinces, vpon condition that conuerſation and commerſe ſhould be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:4320:3"/>and prohibited vnto them, for that were no peace, but a certaine and true baniſhment, which alwayes is deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and excepted betweene enemies and euill doers.</p>
                  <p>Therefore the propoſition made by the Spaniards, to debarre vs from trading into the Eaſt India, firſt ſheweth and declareth a manifeſt kind of vnreaſonableneſſe and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtice. Secondly, an open caution and deceit, by words declaring vs to be a free ſoueraigne State, and in effect ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vs to be of worſe condition, then euer we were vnder Soueraigne Princes, which is wholy without any reaſon or ground: for although we had not traded into the Eaſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies before the warre began, yet we had reaſon, right, and freedome, to haue done it, <hi>Iure gentium,</hi> which was neuer taken from vs by any man.</p>
                  <p>The King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> when hee was Lord of theſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, had no lawfull power, in reſpect of his Spaniards, to take that from vs, for that he was bound by oath, to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and vpold theſe Countries in their freedomes &amp; pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledges of Trading and Traffiquing, whereof without all doubt the free vſe and benefit of the Sea, of the ayre, and of traffick throughout all the world, is the principalleſt point: and doing the contrary, he ſhould haue dealt with vs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to his Oath, in ſuch manner that wee challenge that freedome which from the beginning of the warre wet al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes had, for that free trafficke vpon the Sea, throughout the whole world lies open for vs, whereof without warre and by force, we cannot be debarred nor hindred.</p>
                  <p>And that wee that are Batauians (whoſe liuing depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vpon the Seas) and which are the beſt Marchants, and Sea-faring men, in the whole world, ſhould be debarred or denied of, &amp; fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the vſe of the greateſt part of the Seas, and of the moſt notable parts and traffick of the whole world, is the greateſt preſumption that can or may be imagined, ſpecially when men will extend the ſame, to other King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:4320:3"/>&amp; countries, where they haue nothing to do, &amp; ouer the Seas, ouer the which he hath no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand: the vſe wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of <hi>Iure gentium</hi> is free for all men; and whereof no man in the world hath any particular commaund or authority.</p>
                  <p>And it is ſure, that this ſhould be an vndoubted ſubuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of our eſtate, which in this great warre cannot ſtand and ſubſiſt, without free Trade of Marchandiſe and Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faring, as being the onely meanes that God hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for our maintainance, and the more that the quantity of our Sea-faring and trafficke diminiſheth, according to the ſame proportion, the ſtrength &amp; power of theſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries would alſo bee weakened and decay, for that our Townes and Inhabitants cannot be maintained, much leſſe can we haue any generall power or meanes, by the inlandiſh benefits, of commodities, or rents and reuenewes, as other great Countries and Kingdomes may and can, becauſe our Countrey is too little, therefore we muſt haue all that, out of the Sea and Sea-faring.</p>
                  <p>Now to let you ſee how much we ſhould be hindered, if we ſhould leaue off the Eaſt Indian Trade, and the like hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derance we ſhould conſequently alſo faile of touching the power and ſtrength of theſe Countries. I will proceede to tell you, but firſt I will diſcourſe of the Eaſt Indian Trade, and after that of the Weſt Indies.</p>
                  <p>To make a true eſtimation of the hinderance and hurt as aforeſaid: firſt we muſt vnderſtand, what aduentures and proſperity we haue had by the ſaid Trade. In the Records of the Eaſt Indian Company it appeareth, that from <hi>Anno</hi> 1595. to <hi>Anno</hi> 1601. included, they ſent out 46. ſhips, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of there arriued 43. again in theſe Countries richly laden. Ships that brought for returne, (all charges deducted) two hundred and thirty Tunnes of gold, cleare gaynes for the Marchants of the ſaid Company.</p>
                  <p>Further, by the Records and Bookes of the ſaid Eaſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:4320:4"/>Indian Company: it is alſo ſhewed, that for the ſpace of eleuen yeares wee had ſtill about 30. ſhips continually in Eaſt India, with 5000. Sea-faring men, and that they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected to receiue from thence at leaſt 300. Tunnes of gold in capitall, beſides that which they had in the land. Now I referre it to your iudgement, what the ſaid Company in the laſt enſuing tenne yeares vntill this time hath gayned? who within the time of ſixe moneths, haue had a good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne of 40. Tunnes of gold. I doubt not but you haue heard of the rich lading that the two ſhips brought he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, within the ſpace of a moneth, being valued to bee worth 24. Tunnes of gold, in ſuch manner, that the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular partners from <hi>Anno</hi> 1605. (euery mans full aduenture being deliuered in) haue gayned vpon euery hundred Gil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernes, vntill this day, in ready money, the ſumme of 200. Gildernes, and whenſoeuer any man will ſell his ſtocke (which at this time hee hath in the Company) which hee may doe when hee will, hee may for euery hundred haue 230. Gildernes: whereunto are the Intereſt, which the partners (from the firſt money receiued) to this preſent haue gayned, which alſo is halfe a capitall, there reſteth to the partners particularly, vpon euery hundred, if they haue ventured and traded 16. yeares in the Eaſt Indian Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, in cleare gaynes about 400. Gildernes.</p>
                  <p>I ſpeake not this by report, but as a witneſſe thereof, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one of the partners, that haue receiued my part of the gayne, and may haue the reſt within 8. dayes if I will ſell my ſtocke, which I may at all times doe: but at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent I intend not to doe it, for we hope, that our portions by meanes of our good ſucceſſe in the Eaſt Indian Trade, (wherewith I will hereafter more at large acquaint you) in few moneths will be much better.</p>
                  <p>But it may be, you will ſay, that this profit is great, and very good for the particular partners in the ſaid Company,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:4320:4"/>but what benefit doth thereby ariſe vnto the publique Common-wealth? whereunto I anſwere; firſt, that no Marchants in Trafficking, nor partners in Companies put in their ſtockes, but onely for their owne particular gaine; yet it is moſt true, that the publicke Common-wealth, ſhould bee much more interreſſed, then the particular Traders, by leauing the Eaſt Indian Trade: for beſides this, that the publicke onely conſiſteth of the particular, and that the particular maketh the publicke, and that the publick is powerfull and rich, according to the proportion that the particular hath and aboundeth withall; yet it is moſt true, that the particular without the publick, and not the publick without the particular may be, and ſubſiſt, by this meanes, that the particular going and with-drawing it ſelfe into other Countries, can as well venture from thence into the Indies, as in theſe Countries. But the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick muſt ſtay, and ſee it ſelfe become weake, and decreaſe in force and power, as her Trade and Trafficke decayeth. For according to the proportion thereof, neceſſarily alſo the number of Inhabitants decreaſeth, and the power of the publique likewiſe.</p>
                  <p>Beſides this, conſidering that the Ships and Saylers, that are vſed by the particular Company, are great and many, which without any charge to the Countrey are maintained and paid, and daily employed, vpon all occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents to be vſed by the Countrey, without the which it is impoſſible to haue any power at Sea; as wee ſee and well know, that the greateſt Kingdomes haue no power at Sea, according to the proportion of their puiſſance and might, but onely according to the proportion, of the Trade and Trafficke that they haue and vſe in their Countries.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, we may by the Trade vſed by the ſaid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, vntill the yeare 1614. included, declare and proue, that the cuſtome houſes of the Country, by meanes of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyes,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:4320:5"/>lycences, tolls, and cuſtomes, which the ſaid Eaſt Indian Company haue, and pay, inward and outward, haue profited and receiued aboue 35. Tunnes of gold, for the which the States of the land, haue at ſome times (as neede required) ayded the ſaid Company towards their warres in India, with money and ſhips: partly to eaſe the ſaid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of ſome portion of their charge. Now, what they haue receiued in the cuſtome houſes of the Country, from <hi>Anno</hi> 1614. to <hi>Anno</hi> 1621. without doubt it is a greater ſum, and much more then the former, noting what a rich re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne they haue had within theſe ſeuen yeares.</p>
                  <p>Now to ſhew what furtherance &amp; benefit the common people haue had and gotten by this Eaſt Indian Trade, we muſt note, that a Fleet of 12. ſhips, doth coſt in money and all other things thereunto belonging, about eighteene Tunnes of gold, to ſet and ſend it foorth: and commonly there is not aboue 5. or 6. Tunnes of gold in ready money ſent out with it: all the reſt is bought and prepared here in the land, to the great benefit and welfare of the Countrey, and gayned by the Inhabitants, that ſell and deliuer the ſame. And euery ſhip that comes home againe, one with another, payeth aboue a Tunne of gold for monethly wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, whereby the Officers and Saylers alſo are inriched, which alſo is gotten and ſpent by and among the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants: whereby it is manifeſt, what the common people haue profited; beſides the great number of ſo many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand people, that by meanes of this Trade afore-ſaid, are ſet on worke, and well payd for it, to the great comfort and benefit of many poore people. In ſuch manner, that the laſt yeare when I was at <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> I ſaw not one idle va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gabond nor begger (for ſuch as are ſicke, are prouided for in the Hoſpitalls) goe about the ſtreetes to begge, which good order is alſo obſerued in ſome other Townes.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, to ſhew what the publicke Common-wealth
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:4320:5"/>hath yet further gotten by this Trade, you muſt vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that the greateſt profit of the land conſiſteth in the moſt great hurt and damage which the Enemy hath firſt and laſt endured, and yet endureth in Eaſt India: for ſince that wee were prohibited to Trade and Trafficke in <hi>Spaine,</hi> and other of the Spaniſh territories (which not withſtand againſt his will, by other Nations wee doe continue with good profit) ſome of our Marchants in <hi>Anno</hi> 1595. with reſolute and good courages (which God without doubt endowed them withall) ſayled proſperouſly into the Eaſt Indies, and there firſt began our Trade. And notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, that the Portugales and Spaniards ſought by all the meanes they could at the firſt to debarre and keepe vs from it: neuertheleſſe, wee abſtained not the next yeare, happily to proceed therewith againe. Whereby we being but a ſmall number of Partners in the ſaid Company, brought and procured the mightieſt Potentates of all Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope, to be our Enemies: who well conſidering the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence thereof, ſought all the meanes they could to reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die the ſame, and ioyned the power of <hi>Caſtile</hi> and <hi>Portugale</hi> together, (ſuch and ſo great, as in a hundred yeares before the like was neuer heard of) not onely to let and hinder the proceeding of our happy Trade, or at leaſt to ſtay it a while, but alſo there-withall to be reuenged on the Kings, Princes, and Countries, with whom, in the name of the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> we had a contracted aliance. In reſpect whereof, (the honour and reputation of the Countrey re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring it) it ſought to protect and defend our oppreſſed Company, whereby warre throughout Eaſt Indian (to the great coſt and charges of our Company) began, and yet to the great hurt and hinderance of our Enemies, which may be noted &amp; conſidered hereby, that from <hi>Anno</hi> 1596. wee haue ouercome and ſpoyled eleuen of his great huge Carckets, Gallyes, and other great ſhips, and haue made
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:4320:6"/>about 40. of his ſhips vnſeruiceable; beſides thoſe, that in the laſt tenne yeares enſuing, we haue ſpoyled and taken: whereby our Enemies trade there, hath beene greatly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired, and ours, by Gods bleſſing (who onely is to bee praiſed therefore) to the admiration of the whole world, is greatly encreaſed. In ſuch manner, that the ſtaple of all manner of Spices, and other rich and coſtly Wares, which for the ſpace of 200. yeares together was in <hi>Venice,</hi> (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the ſaid Towne encreaſed and became exceeding rich) and after that by meanes of their Nauigation, was in <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugale,</hi> for the ſpace of 100. yeares: and laſtly, for 25. yeares hath beene in <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Zealand,</hi> and ſince that by a good agreement made, the laſt yeare was alſo brought into <hi>England:</hi> in ſuch ſort, that the King of <hi>Spaines</hi> Marchants, were forced, in the ſaid yeares afore-ſaid (contrary to all mens expectations) to buy Nutmegs, Cloues and Mace, of vs. Now alſo to know what great hinderance the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> receiueth in his Cuſtomes and Tolles yearely, you muſt remember that which I ſhall tell you, all Caracks and Galleons, that are made and prepared by the particular Company, to ſayle outward, muſt not ſayle to Eaſt India, without leaue, and ſatisfying the Kings cuſtome, and being returned againe out of Eaſt India, into <hi>Portugale,</hi> the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors or Partners muſt deliuer a iuſt note of their lading, ſealed vp and ſigned by the Officers in Eaſt India, after that the Officers in <hi>Portugale</hi> agree with the Company or Part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners for the Kings cuſtome, which amounteth to a great ſumme of money, at the leaſt halfe a Capitall: which Wares when they are caried out of <hi>Portugale</hi> into other of the ſaid Kings Kingdomes, muſt againe pay cuſtome, and when they are caried from thence into other Prouinces, the King hath the third and laſt toll of them: all this being calculated into one ſumme, will amount vnto yearely for the King aboue 100. Tunnes of gold, beſides the double
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:4320:6"/>loſſe which the Portugales in 24. yeares haue had and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured firſt &amp; laſt in their ſhips and goods, and yet endure.</p>
                  <p>Hauing ſhewed what the Partners haue profited the Common-wealth, and the Inhabitants thereof, by the Eaſt Indian Trade, and yet doe profit them; as alſo what great damage and loſſe, the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> with his Portugale Subiects by this meanes hath receiued, and endured: now I will briefly declare, the preſent ſtate of the ſaid Company in Eaſt India. You muſt vnderſtand, that matter of Traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficke is in very good termes, which wee hope by Gods help and bleſſing, ſhall from yeare to yeare ſtill be better and better, now the Engliſh-men (by meanes of a contract made with them a yeare ſince) ioyne their forces with ours, and we for our parts haue in Eaſt India, that are comming home and here in the Countrey, aboue 50. ſhips, double furniſhed with luſty Saylers, as alſo all other things fit for the Warre, and for ſo long a voyage, and about 10. ſtrong Forts, whereof ſome we haue taken from the Enemy; the reſt haue beene erected at the great coſt and charges of the Company, and made defenſible, which for the ſecurity of our owne people and goods, as alſo for the defence of our confederates are ſufficiently prouided. Laſtly, when they of <hi>Bantam</hi> began to lay an extraordinary toll vpon our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and cauſed vs to pay 50. <hi>pro cento</hi> cuſtome, and yet we could not for all that obtaine licence of them, to build a Warehouſe of Stone and Morter, for the ſecurity of our Wares and Marchandiſes, for that being of wood, it was twice burnt: we were conſtrained to tranſport our Trade in <hi>Bantam</hi> to another conuenient place, which is a firme Iland, and hath many good and conuenient Hauens in it: for in my Writings I finde, that fiue yeares paſt, <hi>Mataram</hi> the great Emperour of <hi>Iaua,</hi> who is able to bring 300. thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand men into the field, dwelling about 100. miles diſtant from <hi>Bantam,</hi> had alſo ſought to make ſome contract of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:4320:7"/>aliance with vs, offering to deliuer vs Pepper toll free, and licence to build vs a Caſtle of Morter and Stone, with all things conuenient in <hi>Iapara,</hi> which was not well lik'd of by the King of <hi>Bantam,</hi> and his Lieutenant: At laſt our Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on built a conuenient Towne about <hi>Iacatra,</hi> reaſonably well fortified, and called it <hi>Batauia,</hi> where there are about 1000. houſes of all Nations, there to Trafficke and deale in Marchandize, which is defended and gouerned by a Gouernour, Scowt, and other Officers, for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainance of good gouernment and policy, and to admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Iuſtice vnto euery one: and to the end that before all other things, Gods ſeruice and honour might be maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, whereby the blinde Heathens might be brought out of their great darkneſſe, and young children taught the knowledge of the truth of Ieſus Chriſt our Sauiour: the Company diligently and carefully tooke order, to erect a Church and a Schoole therein, to the which end they ſent thether certaine learned men, as at the firſt alſo they did, which with great benefit and encreaſe, haue taught the Heathens the Goſpell of Chriſt in their owne language, as well as vnto our men in their language: In ſuch man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that a King and a Prince of <hi>Amboina,</hi> (where the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey people are much addicted vnto diuelliſh and heathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh ſuperſtitions) ſent two of their ſonnes into theſe Countries, with a Letter written vnto the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> to haue them brought vp at Schoole, and taught our lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, and Chriſtian Religion, that they might at their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne into Eaſt India, be a meanes of planting the Church of Chaiſt there in India, and learne how to defend their owne natiue Countrey. Wee are heartily to pray vnto God, that he will be pleaſed to ſend more true Shepheards thether, that willingly and out of meere loue, will vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take that long voyage, to feed the blinde Sheepe, that they may by meanes of true faith, be brought vnto the fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:4320:7"/>of his heauenly Kingdome and glory: which the Company before all things ought ſpecially to haue a care of, (which I and other of my fellow partners haue heartily entreated them to vndertake, thereunto chooſing ſuch men, as by their godly liues and behauiours, may be an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample vnto others, that ſo our Spirituall exerciſes, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with our temporall Trade of Marchandiſe, may the better be bleſſed, and proſper. This ſhall ſerue onely for an aduiſe, now that I may fully make anſwere vnto your firſt queſtion, I will briefly ſpeake ſomewhat of the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Trade, whereof in the end of your propoſition you make mention.</p>
                  <p>I ſaid before, that notwithſtanding the King of <hi>Spaines</hi> interdiction againſt vs made, touching the ſame, neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe we enioy it by meanes of other Nations: for you muſt certainly be perſwaded, that we were not bereft there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of here in theſe Countries, if you note, that all manufacters, both for price and dealing in other parts into <hi>Spaine,</hi> is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſſoned. In ſuch ſort, that we ſhall win nothing by the Spaniſh Trade, but obtaine a little bettering thereof, yet with doubtfull ſecurity, for if he ſhould graunt vs free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Trade there, then wee ſhall haue liberty to goe thither, which is more then many men thinke of or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, for he for his part thereby, hath his cuſtome, which is very great, and <hi>Spaine</hi> would be victualed by vs in time of need, and we for our parts ſhould put our ſtocks, people, ſhips, and Ordnance into his hands, therewith to oppreſſe our ſelues or our friends, whereunto he would want no oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, as wee haue heretofore well found, and by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence tried, whereof it is needleſſe here to produce any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples.</p>
                  <p>Herewith I wil conclude my anſwer to the firſt queſtion, and proceed to the ſecond, and hauing ſatisfied you there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, I will make a finall reſolution of them both.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <div type="subpart">
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:4320:8"/>
                  <head>The ſecond queſtion.</head>
                  <p>For that wee haue no Townes nor Forts in Weſt India, land the Spaniards for the ſpace of an hundred yeares at the leaſt, haue had &amp; inhabited the moſt part of the Countrey, and the Hauens there, where they trade, with the Indians that now are left therein to their great profit and aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage. It is therefore out of hope, and no apparance at all, that our Weſt Indian Company ſhall be able with any ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage to trade there againſt the Enemies wills, becauſe ſome men are of opinion, that the moſt difficulty will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in the erecting of certaine Colonies in vnknowne pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, where they haue no friends, without the which Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, our Marchants can haue no ſecurity of Trade, as you muſt of force confeſſe, for the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> will not ceaſe, by all the meanes hee can to let and hinder the ſame, and thoſe that liue ſecurely here, will alſo be doubtfull, to truſt their monies out in ſtrange elements, where the winde blowes it away, and where men ſhal not in long time heare of it againe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>Anſwere.</head>
                  <p>I aſſure my ſelfe, when you ſhall haue read my Letter, you will not be doubtfull as you make ſhew of, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I will not ſpare, to put you out of that ſcruple, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to take the like away from others. When wee in <hi>Anno</hi> 1594. reſolued in the yeare enſuing, with a ſmall Fleete (as afore-ſaid) to ſayle into the Eaſt Indies, wee then had no ſorts nor friends in thoſe Countries; neuertheleſſe the Portugales then inhabited, and had ſtrong Townes and Forts therein, and farre ſurpaſſed our power for quantity of ſhips, yet we then began (in the name of God) to Trade there, and notwithſtanding the ſame the next yeare, with good ſucceſſe continued it, (which wee muſt praiſe God for) vntill the yeare of our Lord 1605. and then obtayned a lycence of the States to erect a Company, at the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:4320:8"/>coſts and charges of the ſaid Company, (whereof the Capitall in the ſaid <hi>Anno</hi> 1605. was fully brought in and payd) which amounted vnto about 65. Tunnes of gold: what notable effects (by Gods bleſſing) vntill this time haue enſued thereupon (whereat both the Chriſtians and Heathens themſelues doe wonder) In my former an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, I haue already partly declared, whereby the Spaniſh Trade there, by our Trade, at this preſent is much decrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, whereto the contrary ours yearely encreaſeth: and it is apparant, that at laſt they may be driuen out of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luckoes Ilands, where the Cloues and Nutmegs grow, and (where they get little or no aduantage being ſo much hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred by vs.)</p>
                  <p>Now I will ſpeake of <hi>Guinea,</hi> where alſo at the firſt wee had not one foot of ground, and notwithſtanding that the Spaniards there had ſome ſtrong Forts and friends, yet we Traded there in ſuch manner with 20. ſhips, and 400. men in them, that in time of warre, we dealt there for about 12. Tunnes of gold.</p>
                  <p>Likewiſe at <hi>Punckle del Rey,</hi> in the Weſt Indies, we ſayled Southward with 100. great ſhips, and 1800. men in them, which yearely traded for fraight and Salt, which coſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the fraight, and brought in to the value of 10. Tunnes of gold.</p>
                  <p>The trade for Hides to <hi>Cuba</hi> &amp; <hi>Hiſpaniola,</hi> was followed with 20. ſhips and 1500. men in them, and there we yearely traffick, for 8. Tuns of gold at the leaſt, which in all amoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vnto 180. ſhips, 8700. men, and the returne (by Gods bleſſings) 130. Tunnes of gold, as you may ſee by the calcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation made by the directors <hi>Anno</hi> 1608. which was openly printed and ſet forth the ſame yeare.</p>
                  <p>But for that ſome men without knowledge or vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, diſcourſe and ſpeake of the Weſt Indian Trade, I wil briefly declare, what benefit theſe Countries may reape by the ſaid Trade; which the better to vnderſtand, we muſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:4320:9"/>know, wherein the greateſt part of the riches thereof con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth, which is gotten therein by Spaniards.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, by what meanes we may reape part thereof by Gods help, and hope of good ſucceſſe.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, what furtherance, ſtrength, and power theſe vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Netherland Prouinces, and what good ſucceſſe the partners therein may thereby obtaine.</p>
                  <p>The common opinion is, that the greateſt riches of that Trade conſiſteth in gold and ſiluer Mynes, which are in Weſt India: but it is not ſo; for the greateſt riches at this time conſiſteth in the ſeuerall ſorts of Fruites, and other things that grow therein, as Sugar, Ginger, Indico, Coche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uille, and other drugs, as alſo diuers kinds of wood, hides, pearles, and precious ſtones: and likewiſe in diuers ſorts of Manufactures that are caried thether, whereby the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, Saylers, Peſants, and moſt part of other Handy-crafts men liue. The gold and ſiluer hath beene a great profit vnto the King, when the Spaniards firſt entred into thoſe Countries, where they found great quantity of gold, that had beene gathered together by the Indians in a long time: for the which, ſome millions of poore innocent men, loſt their liues in the Mynes, ſo that the gold at this time is much waſted away, and no more found in ſo great quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and the greateſt riches at this day conſiſteth in the Wares aforeſaid that are caried to and fro.</p>
                  <p>To ſhew this, I wil make no long diſcourſe of the riches, (that beſides gold and ſiluer) come out of the Weſt Indies, but onely ſpeake ſomewhat of <hi>Braſilia,</hi> wherein there is no Mynes of gold nor ſiluer, but onely Sugar, Cotton wooll, Braſill wood, Conſerues and Ginger: but Ginger may not be brought out of <hi>Braſilia</hi> into <hi>Spame,</hi> becauſe they of St. <hi>Domingo,</hi> (who for the moſt part get their liuings there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by,) may not be impoueriſhed. Yet the trade in <hi>Braſillia</hi> is one of the profitableſt trades in Weſt India, whereby the Portugales get moſt profit, and where they (now they are
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:4320:9"/>almoſt bereft of <hi>Guinia</hi> and the Eaſt Indies, or at leaſt get little by them) maintaine their Trade. For out of <hi>Braſillia</hi> yearely one with another, there is brought betweene 40. and 50. thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Cheſts of Suger, which may be valued (2. third parts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing white, and but 1. third part browne Suger) at 25. pounds Flemiſh the Cheſt, then ſay it were 40. thouſand Cheſts, and each Cheſt but 20. pounds Flemiſh, it amounts to 800. thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand pounds Flemiſh, which is 48. Tonnes of Golde, not reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Braſill wood, Cotton wooll, and other wares, which alſo are of great value: and then the manufactures &amp; other wares, that are carried out of <hi>Portugal</hi> thether, which alſo amount vnto aſmuch as the Suger. It is true, that there is much mony alſo carryed thither out of <hi>Portugal,</hi> but that is by reaſon that there is no other manufactures vſed there, then ſuch as the <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugales</hi> themſelues haue need of, but their Slaues, which are many thouſands, haue nothing, becauſe moſt of them goe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and ſo get nothing elſe but their paines for their labours, and of the wilde Braſillians they get no aduantage thereby, becauſe they eſteeme not of the vſe thereof. Where to the contrary, if we were there, we would get great furtherance and aduantage alſo by our labours, and thereby trade would bee much increaſed. By this you may eaſily perceiue, what great riches the wares of Weſt India altogether amount vnto, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo what the wares that are carryed thither doe yeeld. For in <hi>Noua Spania</hi> and <hi>Perto,</hi> in ſome places there are ſome Indians that are polliticke and weare cloathes as we doe. And if the Spaniards, by meanes of their great ſtrength, had not for the moſt part rooted out the Inhabitants, where they command, without doubt, they ſhould haue reaped more furtherance thereby, then now they doe, for that the Indians would haue growne more ciuill and politicke, and to enioy the fruits that proceed from labour, would haue addicted themſelues to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. But now thoſe Countries for the moſt part are vnpeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled of their naturall Inhabitants, and thoſe that ſtill remaine therein, are had in ſuch ſubiection that they haue neither
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:4320:10"/>hearts nor wills, but had rather dye, then liue vnder their go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment. Thus I haue ſufficiently ſhewed, wherein the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the Weſt Indian trade moſt conſiſteth, that is in the Wares and Marchandizes which are in thoſe Countries, and other Countries haue not, yet Golde and Siluer is not amiſſe therewith to encreſe and augment the Trade.</p>
                  <p>The meanes to bee perticipants in this Trade, is to erect ſome Colonies there, and the better to doe the ſame, we muſt ſuffer the Weſt Indian Company to proceed in their Trade.</p>
                  <p>For as in the Article of the Truce it was agreed, that wee might trafique and trade in all places, Hauens, and Townes, that were not vnder the King of <hi>Spaines</hi> command, then there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we are free to deale in <hi>Terra Florida,</hi> the <hi>Antilles,</hi> the whole Sea coaſt of <hi>Guiana:</hi> a great part of <hi>Braſillia,</hi> and ſo forth to the Sraights of <hi>Magellanes;</hi> being 500. miles, where the Spaniards haue no commaund, but onely in <hi>Rio de la Plata,</hi> and further through the ſtraight <hi>De la Maere</hi> in the rich Countrey of <hi>Chili,</hi> and many other Countries and Ilands lying in the South Sea. I ſpeake not of the great riches, that are to be found inward in the Land, which haue aboundance of Gold, and other coſtly Wares and Marchandizes, the people whereof are ſomewhat polliticke, to whom the Spaniards can haue no acceſſe, where wee in time might obtaine their good wills: in which Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries wee might erect our Colonies, and by that meanes tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique there, and without doubt better, conueniently, and with more profit then the <hi>Portugals</hi> and <hi>Caſtellians</hi> doe. But to tell what places at the firſt, were fitteſt to place our Colonies in I thinke it not conuenient, for that were a meanes to ſome to Diſcouer our intent, and thereby the Spaniards might bee forewarned.</p>
                  <p>Now if certaine Colonies were erected, by that meanes we would get the moſt part of the Trade &amp; Trafique in the Weſt Indies into our hands, by reaſon that we can ſell and afford all Manufactures a hundred for one, better cheape then the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards can doe, and thoſe Wares that come out of India are
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:4320:10"/>better cheape vnto vs 50. in the hundred, then vnto them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſtand vs in ſo much more, before we can bring them out of <hi>Spaine</hi> hither, and further our Countrymen by their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry and labour, would aduance themſelues more then the Spaniards.</p>
                  <p>We muſt not likewiſe bee perſwaded, that the Spaniards doe poſſeſſe and inioy all the fruitfulleſt places in the <hi>Weſt Indies,</hi> and that there is none reſting which they haue not in their hands which are good, temperate, fruitfull, and conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient to dwell in, and to reape profit from thence, for wee know that continually hee maketh warre to winne ſome of them, which otherwiſe, by reaſon of the vnfitnes of his great Ships, can not by him be well found out, as alſo by meanes of the reſiſtance, which the Indians there make againſt him, ſome of them are yet vnknowne vnto him.</p>
                  <p>Beſides all this, the <hi>Weſt Indies</hi> are ſo great and ſpacious, that he cannot poſſeſſe the ſame, whereby the fift part of the <hi>Weſt Indies,</hi> are not yet found out by the Spaniards, neither is the fourth part thereof ſubiect to to the Spaniards.</p>
                  <p>Some will make a great doubt in the beginning of theſe matters, becauſe they are of opinion, that it will bee many yeares before there will be any profit or benefit gotten by this Trade: but they vnderſtand it not, for Suger and Ginger are all ready growne, which will be ſo eaſily done, that in a yeare and a halfe or two yeares at the moſt, we ſhall reape fruites of our Plantation. And when wee haue once begun, it will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe euery yeare. I ſay nothing, that there wee may haue Salt, Wood, diuers colours for Dying, Tobacco, and other Wares, where by at the firſt wee may make ſome profit, atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding more.</p>
                  <p>If it bee anſwered, that the <hi>Portugales</hi> and other <hi>Spaniards</hi> haue better and fitter meanes thereunto in theſe Countries then we may haue, for that already they haue ſome Forts and places in the Countrey; I confeſſe it, but when they came firſt thither, then they had not ſo good meanes nor opportunity,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:4320:11"/>neither for Ships nor other thinges, as we now haue, and the rather, for that thoſe Countries are now as well knowne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, as vnto them, and wee haue good meanes, out of ſome places bordering therein, to get and obtaine all whatſoeuer ſhall be needfull and neceſſary.</p>
                  <p>For vs to erect Colonies, which places are not heere to be ſpoken of, but at the beginning the Spaniard was forced to haue all thinges out of <hi>Spaine,</hi> that he had need of, Thus I haue ſufficiently ſhewed, that the meanes to make vs paricipants of the Weſt Indian Trade, is that wee muſt poſſeſſe ſome places therein, with people out of theſe Countries. Now I will alſo ſhew what great furtherance, ſtrength, and commodity theſe Countries ſhall thereby obtaine.</p>
                  <p>To ſhew this I will not ſet downe, the Scituation, tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratenes, wholſome ayre, and good and fruitfull grounds, that are in the ſaid Weſt Indies, neither the great ſtore of Riuers, aboundance of foure footed Beaſts, Fowles, and Fiſhes, nor yet at large declare what Wares and Fruits growe there, but in a word I will tell you, that the Countrey is fit and conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient for planting of Oyle, Wine, Suger, Ginger, Choche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nile, Cotton wooll, Indigo, diuers Drugs, and other Fruits, and to be ſhort, all thinges that <hi>Spaine</hi> and the Weſt Indies yeeldeth vnto vs, and theſe Countries haue not of themſelues, which then neceſſarily muſt needs be a rich Trade.</p>
                  <p>That this Trade, is the richeſt trade in all Europe, I thinke it is without queſtion, for not onely Spaine getteth great ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches thereby, but all Europe alſo hath profited by the ſame. The example of the Spaniſh Marchants may ſufficiently proue it, who were wont to haue a great Trade heere in the Netherlands, but when they began to feele and taſte, what great commodity the Weſt Indian trade brought vnto them, they left this olde Trade to vs, &amp; wholy or for moſt part, dealt in their Weſt Indian trade, whereby beſides the great impoſts and toles that they payed, ordinarily they vſed to get 50. and 100. for a 100. gaines. The <hi>Netherlanders</hi> that dwelt in <hi>Spaine,</hi>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:4320:11"/>and ſecretly had a part in the ſaid gaine, can ſufficiently wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes the ſame, as alſo the great riches which the <hi>Genoueſians</hi> haue gotten from thence.</p>
                  <p>The profit that theſe Countries might reape by our Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factures, will be more then that the Spaniards reape, becauſe we know that the Wares that are ſent from <hi>Spaine</hi> hither, muſt coſt much cuſtome and charges to be carryed from hence thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. That the Marchant was wont commonly to gaine 20. <hi>procento</hi> by the ſame, ſometimes more, ſometimes leſſe. In <hi>Spaine</hi> when it is brought in, the tolles and other charges a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to 20. <hi>procento,</hi> and when it is carryed forth, aſmuch more, and the charges from <hi>Spaine</hi> into the <hi>Indies</hi> are rather more, then from theſe Countries, and if wee gained no more but that which is ſpared, by ſending the Wares from <hi>Spaine</hi> thither, it were more then ſufficient gaine, and I thinke the Marchants and the Weſt Indian Company heere, would bee well pleaſed with halfe thereof.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>That our Manifacture may well be carried thither alſo, it is without all doubt, becauſe it is knowne that in times paſt they were much vſed to be ſent thither by the Spaniards and Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, which now would bee done by thoſe of our Nation that goe to dwell there, to haue them good cheape. And finding the commodity and profit, which they ſhould get by diuers wares comming out of theſe Countries, (as the like hapneth in <hi>Guinea,</hi> and heere without queſtion would bee more when they dwelt among vs) then alſo they would worke, to get ſomething, and to doe it, one would apply himſelfe to Till the ſame, others to worke in the Mines, and Women would ſpin Cotton wooll, and winde Silke, for that by reaſon of the warmth of the Countrey, Silke wormes would proſper well there, which Cotton wooll and Silke, might bee brought hither into theſe Countries, to make Fuſtians and other Wares, whereby we may ſee, that the ſame would yeeld more profit to theſe Countries then to the Spaniards, and what
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:4320:12"/>great furtherance and power theſe Countries might get thereby.</p>
               <p>And for that the Spaniard knowes well, that Trade of Marchandize conſiſteth in bringing of Wares and Marchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizes, from one Countrey into another, and that it is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, that one Countrey ſhould abound in that, whereof the other hath want, Therefore hee will not ſuffer Oyle nor Wine to be planted in the <hi>Weſt Indies,</hi> thereby to maintaine Traffique, whereunto wee ſhall haue much better commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, then the Spaniard or any Countrey in Europe. For when wee ſhall plant Vines, Oliue trees, Orange trees, and Suger there, we ſhall not onely ſerue the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> but alſo other Prouinces and Kingdomes, out of <hi>India</hi> therewith, in ſuch manner, that by the decay of the Spaniſh trade, conſequently, there muſt enſue, a great eclipſe in the King of <hi>Spaines</hi> Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome and Treaſury, whereof I will ſpeake hereafter.</p>
               <p>But to cauſe the Handicrafts men of theſe Countries, to haue good vtterance for their wares, and that in great aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, there ſhall no other Manufactures be ſent out of theſe Countries into <hi>India,</hi> then ſuch as are made heere in theſe Countries. Whereby, and by other the like ordinances, the ſaid Lands will floriſh, and be filled with Inhabitants.</p>
               <p>For that many <hi>Germaines, Eaſt Countrey-men, Engliſh-men,</hi> and diuers <hi>Netherlands</hi> would come hither, to dwell and place themſelues, in theſe vnited Prouinces, ſome in one, ſome in another, where they might beſt get their liuings; yea, and out of <hi>Brabant</hi> and <hi>Flaunders,</hi> many would come hither, to bee releaſed of the Spaniſh yoake, whereby theſe Countries would abound with people. And it is credible, that many Thouſands out of other Countries, would rather goe with their Wiues and Children into the <hi>Weſt Indies,</hi> then dwell vnder the Popiſh Gouernment, for that the voyage being ſhort, it may well bee endured by Women and Children, as many goe from thence into <hi>Spaine,</hi> and few Fleets goe the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but they take many women with them; and this in truth
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:4320:12"/>were no ſmall benefit, for honeſt men that feare God, who in time of bad trading, haue no great meanes to maintaine their houſholds, to prouide a Countrey for them, where they may in good manner get their liuings, and dwell freely without burthen of conſcience, and carne their bread.</p>
               <p>That Sea-faring alſo ſhould hereby be much encreaſed, and many Saylers thereby made, and ſtill entertained, it may be ſufficiently auerred, by that which is formerly ſet downe, for that if the Weſt Indian Trade for Salt and Hides, which wee haue vſed, hath maintained 100. ſhips, what would it be when we ſhould Trafficke (beſides the Salt) for Sugar, diuers kindes of Wood, Oyle, Wine, and other Wares? This being a voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age but of 4.5. or fixe moneths to &amp; fro, which many times we ſpend in a voyage to the Straights, or into <hi>Spaine,</hi> &amp; there would be better allowance then ordinary giuen to common Saylers.</p>
               <p>Againſt this, firſt it might be alledged, that here in the land we haue not men enough to erect Colonies in India. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that our Countrey men by reaſon of the heat in India, are not ſo able to endure the ayre nor labour, and that by reaſon thereof, they could not make ſo much benefit as the Spaniards doe, that doe it onely by their Slaues. Touching the firſt, it is already parrly anſwered, by that I haue ſaid before; that is, that by reaſon of the great Trade, many Marchants &amp; Trades<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of other places would come hether: whereof ſome would goe from hence to India; and for ſuch as are fit for la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring, wee ſhall haue enough out of high Germanie, Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke, Eaſtland, and other Northerne Countries, who for the moſt part are induſtrious people, which Countries are tenne times better peopled then <hi>Spaine,</hi> and there many of the people are ſo poore, that they cannot liue in worſe ſtate (then they doe) by changing their Countrey; beſides this, wee might get many Netherlanders out of <hi>Spaine,</hi> that know what benefit is to be made in India, who alſo would be willing to goe thether; as alſo ſome that are driuen out of <hi>Braſilia</hi> and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:4320:13"/>the <hi>Canarie</hi> Ilands; ſo that we ſhould get men enough out of other Countries, without emptying of theſe Countries, and thereby we might in a manner haue a two-fold Netherlands, both in Eaſt and Weſt India.</p>
               <p>Touching the heat, which may be ſaid would hinder vs, to dwell or labour there, ſhew the contrary thereof, wee neede alledge nothing but experience, which hath taught vs, that the Netherlanders whereſoeuer they come, whether it be in <hi>Spaine,</hi> the <hi>Canaries, Barbarie, Guinea,</hi> or the Eaſt and Weſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, ſurpaſſe all other men in taking paines. And if wee had no other proofe then of the Salt, which is fetcht out of the Weſt Indies in a moſt hote climate, which as I thinke, is the greateſt labour that is in all the world, it were ſufficient to proue it, and yet it hath not beene found, that in any ſhips that ſayled thether, they haue euer left any of their men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind them. And thoſe that once ſayled thether, haue many times gone thether againe. Wee muſt alſo note, that the dayes and nights there, are of an equall length, and that the heat of the day, by reaſon of the long colde nights is much weakened, as alſo by meanes of the continuall Eaſt windes, which yearely blow there: the greateſt labour that is to bee done in the Townes and Sugar Milles, may well bee done in the night time, and touching tilling of the ground, men haue time to doe it from fiue or ſixe of the clocke in the morning, till ten of the clocke: and after that againe after noone from three to ſixe or ſeauen of the clocke in the euening, which is eight or nine houres in a day. There alſo, all the yeare long a man may worke and labour in the fields: but here for the moſt part we cannot, by reaſon of the cold and vntemperate wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the weather alſo many times is ouercaſt, and then it is cold there alſo, and although it raines, yet that raine hinders them not ſo much, as it doth in cold Countries.</p>
               <p>To thinke that the Spaniards with their Slaues, doe more profit by their labour then wee, that alſo is not ſo, for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly men ſay, that vnwilling Hounds catch bad Hares, and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:4320:13"/>that vnwilling labour brings little profit, when men labour as long as you holde a ſticke ouer their backes, all that they doe is without induſtry, doing like Beaſts with great labour: one man of theſe Countries will rid more worke, then three Moores ſhall doo, which coſt them much money: and when they are vnwilling to labour, either they poyſon themſelues, or ſtarue for hunger to ſpite their Maſters, as knowing no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meanes to ſpite and be reuenged on their Maſters, but onely to make their maſters to looſe their money, and by that meanes often times ſome man that by meanes of his Slaues was rich, in a ſhort time waxeth poore when they dye. And when men looke into the great charges and expences which the Portugales and Spaniards are put vnto in their voyages too and fro, wee muſt of force confeſſe, that we gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing great dayes wages, ſhall get more then they, although they ſhould haue their Slaues and Victuals for nothing.</p>
               <p>Heere I would now conclude, if it were not that the great diſtruſt which onely is grounded vpon our ſmall might and power in reſpect of our mighty Enemy, without any reaſon, makes you and ſome others diſcouraged, as I perceiue by your Letters, therefore to content and ſatisfie you herein, I will begin ſomewhat higher, and yet briefly and thereby to gaine better credit, and to make your memory the freſher, I will ſpeake ſomewhat of our former proceedings, and by a true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation approue it: then I ſay, touching our weakeneſſe, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of ſo powerfull an Enemy, wee confeſſe the ſame. But we are taught, by the holy Scriptures, That there is no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence with God to helpe men by great forces, or where their is but a ſmall power. 2. <hi>Chro.</hi> 14.11. That Iſraell ſhould not brag and ſay, mine owne hand hath ſet me free. <hi>Iud.</hi> 7.2.</p>
               <p>So our valiant Anceſtors in their greateſt need, when the Duke of <hi>Alua</hi> ſought to deſtroy the floriſhing <hi>Netherlands,</hi> had their recourſe to the Lord of Sabothes, which is a God of all power, and a protector of thoſe that are oppreſſed, ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of thoſe that feare him with all their hearts, who therein
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:4320:14"/>to this day, neuer failed in their hope, but were graciouſly comforted. For it is knowne to euery one, how that for the ſpace of 50. yeares together, when all things were at the worſt, the Gentlemen deſtroyed, ſome principall Lords beheaded, many thouſands ſpoyled, baniſhed, and runne away, the good Inhabitants purſes drawne dry, and the good Prince of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous memory gone out of the Countrey: the Spaniards be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Maſters ouer all the Countrey, ſo that in mens opinions, we were all in a manner vtterly ouerthrowne, but that God (as I ſaid) put ſuch couragious hearts and conſtant reſolutions into our Anceſtors, that they tooke on them to defend the Countrey, with body, liues and goods, againſt ſo mighty a Potentate, with conſtant perſeuerance and prouidence, as the truth of the cauſe (without the which there is no bleſſing to be expected at Gods hand) on our ſide required, expecting and hoping that God would ſend vs a happy iſſue, as at this day it is manifeſt vnto all the world, and for the which wee praiſe God continually.</p>
               <p>Now ſet the preſent ſtate of the Eaſt Indies before your eyes, whereof I haue already ſpoken, and where wee in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning had not one foote of Land, and at this day we haue ſtrong Fortreſſes, and haue built a good ſtrong Towne, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that the Enemy there, farre ſurpaſſeth vs for power and force, and the beſt and greateſt Trafficke, as alſo in <hi>Guinia,</hi> is now among vs.</p>
               <p>Wherefore then ſhould wee doubt, to ſet a faſt and firme foot in Weſt India, where many thouſand miles of Land are yet reſting, wherein the Spaniards and Portugale neuer dwelt nor Trade, and where there are yet many thouſand Indians, deſire to haue friendſhip and alliance with vs, as there are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong others the valiant Chileſians enemies to the Spaniards, by whom they were yet neuer wholly ouercome. Thinke you that the Indians that remaine in <hi>Perto, Mexico, &amp;c.</hi> when they ſhall haue the leaſt occaſion, to make vſe of our friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, that they will neglect or ouer-ſlip the ſame? wee hope
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:4320:14"/>therefore by Gods bleſſing and his iuſt aſſiſtance, to haue a happy and good ſucceſſe in our proceedings.</p>
               <p>Beſides the eſtranging of the Indians, by meanes of the ſharpe gouernment of the Spaniards, there is another occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſprung vp, which may cauſe the Spaniards to doubt, that the Indies ſhalbe taken from them, if we once ſet a foot there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, that is, the eſtranging that ſpringeth from the Marriages that haue there bin made betweene the Spaniards and the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian Women, and alſo betweene the Indians and Spaniſh women, from whence the <hi>Meſticos</hi> or halfe generations pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, who eſteeme themſelues rather to be Indians then Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards, and for that cauſe are more addicted to the <hi>Indies</hi> their natiue Countrey, then to <hi>Spaine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To giue you a better courage and liking of our <hi>Weſt Indian</hi> Trade, I will ſpeake ſomething of all the notable Victories that we in former yeares, (by the helpe of God) haue gotten in the <hi>Eaſt Indies,</hi> which I will at large ſet downe for the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God, as alſo to ſerue for a teſtimony of his Fatherly care and fauour towards thoſe, that with all their hearts put their truſt and confidence in him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Andreas de Furtado de Mendoza,</hi> Generall of the Spaniards in Eaſt India, hauing gathered a great fleet of Ships in <hi>Goa, Cochin,</hi> and <hi>Mallacco,</hi> being 30. Ships, whereof 8. were Galli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and 22. Gallies and Fuſts well furniſhed, determined in <hi>Anno</hi> 1601. in the month of Auguſt, to beſiege <hi>Bantam</hi> both by Water and by Land, there by force to hinder our Trade, but being hindered from the fame by ſtormes and contrary windes that happened, he arriued before <hi>Bantam</hi> vpon the 24. of December, the ſame day that <hi>Wolfaret Hermans,</hi> with three Holland Ships and two Pinnaces by Gods wonderfull prouidence, alſo arriued there. It is a common vſe among the Netherland ſhips, that when they haue paſt the Cape <hi>De bona Sperance,</hi> they draw in their Ordnance, as thinking them from thence to the Straights of <hi>Sunea,</hi> to be needleſſe to be vſed, and by that meanes had bin likely to haue fallen into the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:4320:15"/>hands of the ſaid Portugall Army, if God (a thing worthy to be noted) had not ſent them an vnexpected meſſenger before hand, that made them acquainted with all that had bin done. This meſſenger was a man of <hi>China,</hi> who with his Boate came aboard of thoſe Ships, when they were out of fight of the Portugales, thinking to doe them a ſpeciall pleaſure and good ſeruice, thereby to giue them aduiſe to ſhun the danger that they might fall into by meeting with that great Army. Our Ships to whom this meſſage was brought, were called the <hi>Gelderland,</hi> of 500. Tonnes, the <hi>Zealand</hi> of 400. tonnes, the <hi>V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erecht</hi> of 260. tonnes, the 2. Pinnaces, the one was 140. tonnes, the other 56. tonnes, which ſayled out of the <hi>Teſſell</hi> in Aprill, 1601. who in ſteed of hoyſing vp of their Anckers, God gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing them courage, tooke another reſolution, for the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall aforeſaid, aſſoone as he vnderſtood that newes by the man of <hi>China,</hi> willed the Anchors to be caſt out, and calling the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers together, after they had made their prayers vnto God, they tooke counſell together what was beſt for them to doe, for the welfare of their ſmall fleete, for the vpholding in time to come of the Eaſt Indian Trade, and for the honour of the Netherlanders: whereupon they fully determined and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, that confidering the waightines of the buſines in hand, whereon the preſeruation of <hi>Bantam</hi> conſiſted, or the vtter o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow thereof, whereby it was euident what loſſe and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drance the vnited Prouinces might therby reape and ſuſtaine, truſting vnto God for his mercifull ayde, they fully determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned valiantly to fall vpon the Portugall army, thereby to driue them from thence, and vpon the ſame reſolution, preſently all their Cabbens and other things that might hinder them were puld downe and caſt ouer-bord, to the end that when need re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, freely vſe their great Ordnance, and euery man perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally ſtand to his defence againſt the enemy as need required; The Ordnance being cleared, and all things ready prepared for ſuch a fight, being ſet in order, the next morning at two of the clocke before day-light, vpon a ſigne made by fire, they
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:4320:15"/>hoyſed vp their anchors, about Sunne riſing, being the 25. day of December, and about the ſame time were in ſight of the Portugales, and after they had fought eight dayes together with them, draue them from thence, and forced them to run away, their ſhips being ſhot through with the Ordnance, and ſixe ſhips loſt, whereof two we tooke, they themſelues ſetting fire on two of them, and two were ſhot vnder ground, &amp; for our parts loſt but one man, but many hurt, and with great ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour went backe to <hi>Bantam,</hi> wherein few dayes they repaired their ſhips. At this triumphant victory, not onely the Indian Kings and Princes, but alſo the ghoſtly Father of his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, <hi>pater Iohn Nay</hi> (when he in <hi>Anno</hi> 1607. was in the <hi>Hage</hi>) much wondred, and finding occaſion to ſpeake with the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall <hi>Wolfart Hermans,</hi> he asked him what moued him to be ſo hardy and bold, to ſet vpon ſo mighty a Fleet of ſhips, which for ſhips and men was three times ſtronger then his was, whereby it was apparant, that both he and his men were likely to be ſpoyled by them. He made him anſwere, that he was aſſured of Gods gracious ayde, who endowed them with ſuch manly courage, and that before they would haue per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the Enemie to bee Maſters of them and their goods, they would haue ſet fire on their powder, and at one inſtance would haue blowne their Enemies and themſelues vp into the ayre. I haue written this battaile ſomewhat more at large, intending not to make rehearſall of the braue victory gotten by <hi>Matelief</hi> before <hi>Malacca,</hi> and of <hi>Stephen Verhaghen</hi> before <hi>Ambyna,</hi> &amp;c. becauſe I will bee briefe, the honour onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing vnto God, who giueth his ſeruants couragious harts to effect great matters, and to bring them to paſſe, to whom be praiſe and glory for euer Amen.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, you write that ſome men that liue here in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, will be doubtfull to truſt their mony in ſtrange elements, where the winde blowes it away, and whereof in long time, men ſhall not heare againe. All theſe doubts, by that which is ſaid before, are ſufficiently taken away, but to ſuch as haue
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:4320:16"/>not read the Letters Patents made and graunted to the Weſt Indian Company, by the generall States, I ſaid, You know how the Eaſt Indian Company began particularly without any ayde from the Countrey, and with indifferent benefit, and furtherance to the particular partners, by Gods bleſſing, ſtill continue the ſame, whereof the profit would haue beene two times greater, if they had not beene preſſed with exceſſiue great charges, touching warre, for the maintainance of the Eaſt Indian Trade, and the defence of themſelues and their allies. Whereas the Weſt Indian Company, are graunted a notable ayde to be giuen them by the generall States, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of their great charges, for they are promiſed, that they will defend &amp; protect their Company in their free Sea-faring and Trade, and to that end help them with a ſum of money of ten 100. thouſand Gilderns, to be payd in fiue yeares, whereof the firſt 200. thouſand Gilderns ſhall be furniſhed, as ſoone as the firſt payment among the partners ſhall be made, and when they haue furniſhed the halfe of the ſaid ten 100. thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Gildernes, they ſhall haue their benefit of the gaine and profit as all other partners in the ſaid Company ſhall haue. And further, when ſo euer the matter within the limits of the Company, ſhall proceed to an open war; the States promiſe to ayde the ſame further, with twenty Shippes, well mounted and appointed of all things, as alſo of braſſe and other Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and a conuenient quantity of amunition, together with double ſayles, ropes, anchors, and other things accordingly. And that when theſe Countries are ſomewhat eaſed of their great charges which now they are at, and that the ſaid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany ſhould happen to bee put to great charges, by reaſon of warres, the ſaid Company ſhould haue an amends made them of the ſaid Subſidie, as much as the ſtate of the land would permit. Vpon theſe benefits and graunts, without doubt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thouſands will willingly contribute thereunto, ſpecially when they ſhall vnderſtand, that the Trade to <hi>Guinea</hi> and to the Salt Countries, is alſo comprehended in the Weſt Indian
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:4320:16"/>Company, which trades yearely haue made good returnes, as I haue already partly ſhewed, which alſo will partly lighten the burthen of the Company; whereof when the partners ſhal be well informed before, wherein (with this diſcourſe I would willingly ayde them) they wil the readilier contribute, which by my ſelfe I haue found: for being reſolued, (for the loue of my Country) to put in a portion, after that I was better infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of the matter, I doubled the ſame. And this is certaine, that there wil a great number contribute vnto the ſame, whoſe hearts are by God ſtirred vp thereunto, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.27. in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter whereof I hope your name will be one, although there ſhall not want money for the erecting of this notable Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, for the which ſo many thouſand good Patriots the laſt yeare did long and wiſh after: for if ſome particular perſons, at their owne coſts &amp; charges (as afore-ſaid) in time of warre, raiſed, furniſhed &amp; ſet forward 140. great ſhips to ſayle South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to <hi>Guinea, Cuba,</hi> and <hi>Eſpaniola,</hi> and ſtill kept them in Trade. How much greater then ſhall this Fleet be, (by Gods bleſſing) being endowed with ſo great furtherances and priuiledges, for the eaſe &amp; benefit of the partners, by the general States: for the which preparation ſome other Common-wealths, and many thouſands, that are not of the vnited Netherlands, will parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipate with vs. We muſt alſo conſider, that for the price that one Eaſt Indian ſhip doth coſt to ſet it out, &amp; in 17. moneths brings home her returne, we may for the mony ſet out 3. or 4. Weſt Indian ſhips, with hope of 2. returnes in a yeare, which ſhippes may alſo be ſent out 12. voyages one after the other, without reparations, which will alſo eaſe vs of a great part of our charges. Now to conclude, I muſt anſwere you to your propoſition, of ſtrange elements, wherby you vnderſtand, that we ſhould both loſe our capitall &amp; benefit all together. In tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting to the venture of the Seas, I beleeue the laſt well, but that we ſhould loſe both capitall and profit by this Fleet, I hope that God will neuer permit it, but thoſe that deliuer out their moneyes for firme rents, or for any ſuch pawnes, are not
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:4320:17"/>they ſometimes ſubiect to ſuch chances, ſpecially in time of warre: yea, and in time of peace it often times falls out, that the honours in twenty yeares doe not receiue their principall money layd out for their deare bought lands, where men in time of warre, by the Indian Trade, haue receiued fiue or ſixe principall ſtockes, by the Spaniſh Trade men in time of peace yearely gayned 20. <hi>pro cento,</hi> when their Trade proſpered, which profit the Indians and other Marchants, alſo in time of warre; by other Countries (as I ſaid before) got out of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and yet get alwayes the returne that ſhall come out of the Weſt Indies, will farre ſurpaſſe others, when wee ſhall haue planted ſome Colonies there (as wee hope we ſhall) and it is apparant, that many thouſand Indians, will ioyne with vs, and deliuer the hill of <hi>Potoſy</hi> and other places, (where the Mynes of gold and filuer are) vnto vs: yet if this at the firſt will not fall out ſo, wee will gladly content our ſelues with the other rich commodities and great bleſſings, which it ſhall pleaſe God to ſend vs, wherewith thoſe Countries aboue all others are richly furniſhed, as we at large haue already ſhewed.</p>
               <p>This is that which I thought good to write, for an anſwere vnto your queſtions afore-ſaid, and other doubts by you made, nothing doubting but that all good Patriots, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fire the good, benefit, and proſperity of our natiue Country, will not at any time take on them, with a good conſcience, to ſpeake or giue counſell to leaue off the Eaſt and Weſt Indian Trades, that wee may hold and enioy an vncertaine Spaniſh Trade, not that wee doe not in any ſort long and wiſh after a godly, vpright, generall, and continuall peace: but becauſe we deſire not vnder the ſhew thereof, to be deceiued. Alwaies the neceſſity of the ſaid Indian Trades, for two reaſons is ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially thought conuenient. The firſt, that the free Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands confidering their cituation, and the manner of liuing vſed by the Inhabitants thereof, cannot continue in their flouriſhing ſtate and welfare, wherein (notwithſtanding the warre) they now are, if their Ships, rich Hauens, and Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faring
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:4320:17"/>men, and rich Marchants Towne, haue not free Trade and trafficke at Sea. The ſecond conſidering the King of <hi>Spaines</hi> might and riches, in all reſpects, the <hi>Netherland</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces muſt be perſwaded, that there is no better meanes in the world to be found, whereby to be releaſed of that conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall feare, then to vndermine the foundation of his great ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches to bereaue him of a good deale of his Eaſt and Weſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian Trade, In ſuch manner, that by meanes of the fire in the Eaſt and Weſt Indies ſo kindled, the Spaniards ſhall in ſuch manner decline, that all the world ſhall warme it ſelfe by that fire, for that the Marchants thereby, vpon the eclipſe of the Spaniſh Trade, will disburſe no money before hand.</p>
               <p>And although the firſt neceſſity of the Trafficke be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yound Seas, may be ſome be contradicted and anſwered in this manner, that it followeth not thereupon, that we muſt of force Trafficke into <hi>India,</hi> but rather if we haue peace, we might againe haue and vſe our olde Trade into <hi>Spaine,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, although before I made anſwer to the ſame, yet for ſome pregnant reaſons, I will againe repeat them, that it may the better be vnderſtood, and briefly ſaid, Firſt that the Spaniſh Trade, can not be aſſured vnto vs, for that the Spaniards by a hundred wayes will finde meanes (whereunto they will not want pretences) to make it vnprofitable for vs, as by his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, Toles and Proclamations, as of late yeares it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Secondly, it is altogether dangerous, for that if the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy hath any great enterpriſe in hand, by that meanes (wee hauing put our ſelues into the hands and power of our recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled Enemy,) he may not onely haue many hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand meanes to hinder vs, but ayde himſelfe by our Ships, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance and Saylors in great numbers, to our great detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which Spaniſh Trade alſo, notwithſtanding, in time of Warre, by meanes of the Engliſh and Frenchmen, we haue v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with indifferent good gaine; therefore it is altogether to be diſliked, and not conuenient for vs, vpon ſuch tearmes to treate with the Spaniard.</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:4320:18"/>
               <p>But now my Lords the States generall vpon premeditated ripe deliberation and good aduiſe, (without doubt by the good prouidence of God) haue generally graunted the <hi>Weſt Indian</hi> Trade to goe forward, and haue endowed the ſame with notable priuiledges, whereunto many good Patriots ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their meanes, haue willingly begun to contribute. The Spaniards will not ceaſe to vſe a thouſand practiſes, to fruſtrate and make voyde the ſaid States good reſolutions, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by ſome Marchants or other Fauorites, whom they will ſeeke to ſtroake with the golden ſtaffe of <hi>Peru,</hi> yet with thoſe that are good and honeſt, to no end, who for no worldly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect will be moued vnto ſo hurtfull and diſhonorable reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, being aſſured, that at the laſt, thereby will enſue the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion of this great ſtate, and conſequently of all their Allies and adherents.</p>
               <p>But now ſome men will ſay, that wee ought to keepe in our Countrey, without ſeeking to extend our commaund by Colonies beyond the Seas, that wee may keepe and defend that we haue. That is but a bad counſell, for his power, by our Trade in <hi>Eaſt India</hi> (as aforeſaid) is much decayed, and if God (whom we muſt pray vnto for that grace) will giue vs a good ſucceſſe in the <hi>Weſt Indies,</hi> hee will without doubt deſire Peace with vs, which for our ſecurity hee will religiouſly keepe and maintaine, onely not to loſe a great part of his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian reuenue, whereunto we haue good hope, for the reaſons before, at large by vs ſet downe.</p>
               <p>Then hauing ſhewed, how theſe Countries, by the trade be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Seas, (by Gods bleſſing) haue euen in the middle of their Wars encreaſed in Trade, people, &amp; wealth, (which are the Sinewes of this Common-wealth) ſo wee muſt confeſſe that the <hi>Eaſt Indian</hi> Trade, hath wrought two notable effects. It hath increaſed the meanes of our natiue Countrey, with no ſmall decreaſing of the Spaniſh Trade in <hi>Eaſt India.</hi> For the which, God is eternally to bee praiſed, and hauing alſo ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that yet better ſucceſſe by the <hi>Weſt Indian</hi> Trade, is (by
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:4320:18"/>Gods bleſſing) to be expected. Then all good Patriots ought to encourage one the other, (ſeeing that they cannot better imploy their money, for more and greater reputation for the Countrey then ſo) liberally to contribute their money for the ſetting forth of this Fleet in 3. payments, whereof the firſt ſhall be payed the laſt of Nouember, which next vnto God, will be a ſoueraigne meanes to holde the Enemy in ballance, and keepe vs and all our neighbours and friends, in peace without any feare, if in mans Iudgement and conſideration, there be any ſecurity to be had.</p>
               <p>Tu conclude, I beſeech God, to be pleaſed to hold his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hand ouer this Fleet, and to ſtrengthen it with his ayde, and ſo to direct it, that thereby our Enemies may be weakened and ouerthrowne, and wee ſtrengthned and made powerfull, and yet neuertheleſſe not to embolden our ſelues vpon our owne power, but onely to reſt vpon God, and with humble hearts and bended knees to thanke him for the ſame, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit our ſelues to his Fatherly protection. Commending the Lords the generall States, his Excellency the Prince of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range,</hi> and all other Noble perſonages, and valiant Souldiers vnto God.</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Vale.</salute>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Written in haſt</hi> 
                     <date>
                        <hi>the Firſt of September.</hi> 1621.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:4320:19"/>
            <p>And to ſhew our <hi>Batauiaens</hi> in Eaſt India, in the beginning haue bin entertained of Kings and Princes, notwithſtanding the Portugales and Ieſuites, ſought to hinder the ſame, with ſome of them, by ſcandalous reports. You may reade the Coppie of a Letter that <hi>Signeur Arenet ten Grotenhuyſe</hi> a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant and partner wrote vnto Mr. <hi>N. N.</hi> from <hi>Amſterdam, Anno,</hi> 1610. the 29. of Iuly, as followeth.</p>
            <p>GOod Friend, hauing read the Letters that came out of <hi>Eaſt India,</hi> and examined the Commiſſioners, I thought good to make you perticipant thereof, which is, that the Admirall <hi>Verhoeff</hi> thinking it expedient to ſend two Ships (namely the <hi>Lyon</hi> with piles, and the <hi>Griſon,</hi> which hee had left there for the Defence of <hi>Ihoor</hi>) to the Iſland of <hi>Iapan,</hi> there to obtaine Licence of the Emperour freely to Trade, and to make a Contract with him touching the ſame, according to the Letters by the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> written vnto the ſaid King, and the inſtructions of the Partners to that end alſo gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. And aſſoone as thoſe Ships had receiued thoſe Letters and Commiſſion from the Admirall, they hoyſed vp their Anchors before <hi>Booz</hi> and ſet ſayle, holding their courſe to <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taua,</hi> and taking in ſome Silke, vnwrought, Silke ſtuffes, and ſome Pepper, in the beginning of Iune <hi>Anno,</hi> 1609. they ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to <hi>Iapan,</hi> and vpon the Firſt of Inly anchored before the Towne of <hi>Firando,</hi> lying vnder the height of 33. Degrees, and 20. minutes, where our men were well and friendly receiued and entertained by the Gouernour, and Magiſtrates of the place, and for that the Gouernour of that part of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey was in fewe dayes after to goe vnto the great Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour to ſalute him, (which throughout all the Kingdome once a yeare is to bee done by euery Gouernour) they perſwaded our Committee, that hee ſhould alſo preſently goe thither with him, that ſo the Portugales and Ieſuites, that reſide in <hi>Hageſacke</hi> about eighteene miles from <hi>Furando,</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:4320:19"/>might not preuent them, nor hinder in their ſute, which our Committees conſidering of, made preparation to goe, hauing firſt gotten letters of commendation from the Gouemour of <hi>Furando,</hi> and taking ſome preſents with them, ſet forward on their iourney, accompanied with a Netherlander called <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chior van Sandtuoore,</hi> that had dwelt tenne or twelue yeares in that Countrey, and was left of <hi>Mahews</hi> Fleet, with about ten perſons more, and could ſpeake Spaniſh very well, and alſo ten or twelue perſons of good quality, that were appointed to goe with them, that no hurt might be done vnto them by the way, and ſo trauailed for the ſpace of 14. dayes by water, and eight dayes on horſebacke by land, about 300. miles, paſſing through many faire built and well inhabited Townes, where in euery place they were well and honourably entertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, till at laſt they came to a great faire Towne, wherein the great King or Emperour of <hi>Iapan</hi> holds his Court, where they preſently addreſſed themſelues vnto, and had audience of two great Lords neere attending vpon the King, who forthwith brought them into the Kings preſence, and got audience for them, where they were moſt friendly welcommed and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained both by the ſaid two Lords, and the King, and hauing ſhewed the cauſe of their comming, and buſineſſe with the King, and deliuered the Preſents and Letters of Prince <hi>Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice</hi> vnto him, the Emperour ſhewed them a moſt friendly countenance, telling them, that hee liked well of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming with their Shippes and of themſelues, asking after the manner and cituation of our Countrey, and what manner of man our Prince was, of whom by the men that were of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiens</hi> Ships, he had formerly-heard much ſpeaking, and alſo had heard of the valour of our men, in the battailes fought by our Ships in India, againſt the Portugales, ſpecially of thoſe of <hi>Malucco,</hi> ſaying that he was ſorrie that our Ships arriued not in ſome Hauen neerer vnto his Court, that he might ſhew vs greater courteſie, and ſo graunted vs our requeſt, for free trading and commerſe in his Country and whole Kingdome,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:4320:20"/>and for that he vnderſtood that no agreement could be made betweene vs and the Portugales, hee graunted vs therefore as free licence to traffique and negotiate in his Countrey, as any of his owne people and ſubiects haue. Three dayes before the arriuall of our Committees there, ſome Portugales and Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites were come to the Court, vſing all the meanes they could to make vs diſtaſtfull to the King, and to hinder vs from ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing acceſſe vnto the Emperour, but all in vaine; for that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>before we came, they could get no audience of the great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonages, nor yet of the Emperour: and after that our men had beene 10. dayes at the Court, and there ſeene great mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence, riches, and glorious ſhewes, they obtayned lycence of the Emperour to depart, who gaue them an open Letter written vnto the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> in <hi>Iapan</hi> language, brauely ſealed vp, and to the end that wee ſhould know the contents of the ſaid Letter: it was by one of the Iapeners read vnto vs, and put into Dutch by foure or fiue of our Nation, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents thereof being as followeth, I Emperour and King, &amp;c. our men cannot ſufficiently ſet downe the firtillity and fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of the Countrey, abounding in Rice, Wheat, Goats, a great number of dried and freſh Fiſh: all kindes of trees, and fruits of the earth, as Apples, Oranges, Lemonds, and many other fruits, which are common with vs. They haue good policy and lawes in their Countrey, they are a kinde of witty and courteous people, amongſt them hauing many rich men which are Heathens, onely about <hi>Hageſar,</hi> where the Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugales dwell, there are ſome Chriſtians. This land buyeth many kinde of Manufactures of our Countrey, and hath good ſtore of gold and ſiluer, many rich Mynes of Copper, and ſtill more and more are found: the Emperours reuenew of Gold and Rice is innumerable, our men vnderſtood by thoſe of <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pan,</hi> and alſo by the Netherlands, that the Tower in the Caſtle was full of Plate, Gold and Siluer, in ſuch great pieces, that ten men could hardly lift them.</p>
            <p>They alſo ſaid, that the Countrey lyes much more Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:4320:20"/>then it is ſet downe in our Cards, and that it reacheth about 23. degrees, and 48. minutes more Northerly, it is full of diuers Townes; ſo that as you trauell through the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, euery three or foure miles you ſhall finde a Towne, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Villages that lie betweene them. It is full of hills, which from the bottome to the top are fruitfull, as alſo faire flat valleyes, many riuers, ponds and pooles. The Emperour hath 66. Kings vnder him, hee is a man of about 60. yeares old, and two yeares agoe hee cauſed his ſonne to be crowned, which hath his Court at <hi>Eden,</hi> lying vpon a faire riuer, about three miles broad.</p>
            <p>And ſo hauing beene tenne dayes in the Court, they went againe to their Ship lying at <hi>Firando:</hi> and after they had there hired a houſe for our men, vpon the 1. of October <hi>Anno</hi> 1609. they departed from thence, leauing one <hi>Iaques Phillips</hi> there for their chiefe Marchant, one vnder Factor, and three more, in all fiue perſons, with an indifferent ſtocke: and from thence ſet ſayle for <hi>Pataua,</hi> where they tooke in more Pepper, raw Silke, and Silke Clothes, and with it returned home into the Netherlands, arriuing heere with all their men whole and ſound vpon the 20. of Iuly, hauing loſt but three men that were ſicke and dyed in the voyage, from <hi>Iapan</hi> hether, &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
